Guide to the Henry Raup Wagner Collection of Philip Nolan Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Raup Wagner collection of Philip Nolan papers
1797-1808
WA MSS S-344
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
The Philip Nolan papers document his expeditions from Louisiana into Texas in the years 1791-1801 and the reaction of the Spanish governors of Texas and Nuevo Santander, including the trial of Nolan's men by the Spanish.
Wagner, Henry R. (Henry Raup), 1862-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was formerly owned by Edward Everett Hale. Purchased from Henry Raup Wagner in 1919.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Philip Nolan papers document his expeditions from Louisiana into Texas in the years 1791-1801 and the reaction of the Spanish governors of Texas and Nuevo Santander, including the trial of Nolan's men by the Spanish.
Texas -- History -- To 1846; Public officers -- Spanish; Ashley, Robert, fl. 1803-1805; Bautista, Juan; Bean, Peter Ellis, 1783-1846; Blackburn, Ephraim, 1754-1807; Cooley, Zalom; Danlin, William; Eastridge, Colwell; Eastridge, Miles; Fero, David; Flóres, Manuel Antonio de; Guadiana, José Maria; House, Thomas; King, Charles, fl. 1801; Leal, Antonio, 1750-ca. 1802; Leal, Gertrudis de los Santos; McKay, Simon; Nolan, Philip, 1771-1801; Osé, Lucas; Pie, Jose del; Pierce, Joel; Reed, Joseph, fl. 1801; Richards, Mordecai; Richards, Stephen; Walters, Johan; Galindo Navarro, Pedro; Garcia de Texada, Antonio; Nacogdoches (Tex.). Comandante; Provincias Internas (New Spain). Comandante General (1792-1804: Nava); Provincias Internas (New Spain). Comandante General (1804-1813: Salcedo); Texas. Governor (1799-1805: Elguezabal)
- Box and folder list
  - Guadiana, José María
    - Causa seguida a los individuos Anglo-Americanos ... y con siete individuos de la nacion Espanol se hallaron en union de Don Felipe Nolan .... [Nacogdoches, Tex]., [1801] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Contains: Testimony of the prisoners, letters of Nolan, documentary evidence, and correspondence between Guadiana and other officals concerning the case.
    - Diligencias practicada en Nacogdoches para evacuar la cita hechos por David Fero uno de los companeros de Dn. Felipe Nolan ...., [1801] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      At head of title: Texas. Ano de 1801. Contains deposition of Manuel Flores.
    - Informaciones tomadas por mi Dn. Jose Maria Guadiana, sobre el Reo Lucas Ose, a los Americanos Colbers Estraigd [!] y Miles Estraigd [!] en 20 Septiembre de 1797. [Nacogdoches, Tex.], 1797 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Depositions of Colwell and Miles Eastridge, witnessed by Philip Nolan.
  - Informacion expuesta por ochos testigos acerca de la conducta de Antonio Leal, de su mujer Gertrudis de los Santos, la amistad, trato y comunicacion que estes dos han tenido con Don Felipe Nolan. Nacogdoches and Bexar, Tex., 1801 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains depositions, documentary evidence, and correspondence of Guadiana, Elguezabal and Nava on the case.
  - Insidencias de la causa de los Espanoles y Anglo-Americanos. V.p., [1803-05] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, mainly between the commandant at Nacogdoches, the Governor of Texas and Comandante of the Provincias internas, about a rumored expedition to Texas by Robert Ashley, one of Nolan's associates.
  - Nacogdoches, Tex. Comandante. Diario de las Novedades Ocurridas en la salida que Yo Dn. Miguel Francisco Musquiz ... Compte. del Puerto de Nacogdoches. Verifico el quatro de Marzo de mil ochocientos uno en solicitud de el Americano Felipe Nolan y Quadrilla que le acompana ...., 1801 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Diary covers period 14 Mar - 3 Apr 1801. Detailed account of the death of Nolan and capture of his party.
  - Provincias internas, Mex. Comandante general (Nava). Expediente relating to expenses incurred in keeping and transferring the prisoners from Nolan's Texas expedition. V.p., 1801-08 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Reports, letters, accounts, receipts and orders.
  - Provincias internas, Mex. Comandante general (Salcedo). [Expediente] Sobre fuga intentada por los Anglo-Americanos presos en el quartel de Chihuahua y presidio de San Carlos., [1804] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    At head of title: Texas. Año de 1804. Investigation of an attempted escape by the survivors of Nolan's expedition.
  - Richards, Mordecai. Ynstancia de Mordica [!] Richards ... pidiendo de los que acompanaron a Dn. Felipe Nolan: y resolucion del S. Cmandte. Gral. accediendo a dha. Solicitude., [1805] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    At head of title: Texas. Ano de 1805.
  - Texas (Province) Gobernador (Elguezabal). Expediente relating to Philip Nolan's activities in Texas and the imprisonment of his men. V.p., 1797-1804 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Mainly correspondence between the Governor of Texas and the Comandante general of the Provincias internas, but includes some earlier correspondence with Nolan.
  - Ynstancias presentadas al Sr. Comandte. Gral. por los Anglo-Americanos companeros de Nolan sobre diversas solicitudes: y resoluciones de S.S. acerca de ellas., [1806] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    At head of title: Texas. Anos de 1803 a 1806. Petitions of the prisoners and replies to them.